A Guide to the Joseph Larner Laboratory Research Papers, circa 1990-2014
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Joseph Larner Laboratory Research Papers, circa 1990-2014
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-60
3 boxes with the dimensions of 5.5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches
University of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was assembled by Douglas Heimark and transferred from the Larner Laboratory in the University of Virginia's Aurbach Medical Research Building at Fontaine Research Park to the University of Virginia Claude Moore Health Sciences Library on 31 July 2014.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Joseph Larner (1921-2014) was renowned for his work in the fields of pharmacology and biochemistry. Larner's accomplishments include serving as Chairman of the UVA Department of Pharmacology from 1969-1990, founding the UVA Diabetes Center for research in 1974, and receiving the Banting Medal for Scientific Achievement in Diabetes Research from the American Diabetes Association in 1987. His research, which he continued into his 90s, included the discovery of a carbohydrate compound, or glycan, made up of D-chiro-inositol and Galactosamine. D-chiro-inositol is a naturally occuring carbohydrate which is deficient in many patients with insulin resistance diseases; Galactosamine is an amino sugar. The compound isolated and later chemically synthesized by Larner's laboratory, called INS-2, was shown to help lower blood sugar, and was the focus of much of Larner's research. The Larner laboratory worked to isolate the enzyme responsible for producing D-chiro-inositol in the body and also searched for the relevant gene. INS-2 continues to be studied by some of Larner's collaborators today. During his time at UVA, Larner worked with many promising scientists, two of whom later won Nobel Prizes: Alfred Gilman and Ferid Murad in 1994 and 1998 respectively. Dr. Joseph Larner died 28 January 2014.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 23 folders containing research notebooks from the Larner laboratory dated 1990 to 2014 and a bibliography of Larner's work from 1949 to 1999. The research was recorded by Douglas Heimark, a Senior Pharmacology Laboratory Research Specialist in the Joseph Larner Laboratory, and primarily pertains to the study of INS-2 and insulin resistance in cases of Type II diabetes, PCOS, preeclampsia, and Alzheimer's.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in folders by subject and chronology.
Contents List
- Joseph Larner, M.D., Ph.D. Bibliography of published papers and presentations, 1949-1999 (Box-folder 1:1)
  Two versions of the bibliography are included; the second reflects corrections make by Douglas Heimark in 2014
- Six Nobel Laureates Associated with Joseph Larner, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
- Joseph Larner Laboratory summary written by Douglas Heimark, 2014 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Gas chromatography/flame ionization detector (GC/FID), and Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS) lab results, 1992 July 9 - 1997 February 26 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS) lab results, 1992 September 21 - 1998 January 14 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Rat liver (RL) prep 1, and Bovine liver (BL) preps 28-37, 1997 February 7 - 1999 April 2 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 39-53, 1999 March 4 - 1999 October 4 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 56-69, Rat liver (RL) prep, and Lipid mediator notes, 1999 October 13 - 2001 June 18 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Laboratory notebook of William T. Henshaw: Bovine liver (BL) preps 73-88, and Rat liver (RL) prep 5-7, 2002 May 21 - 2004 October 28 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 70, 80-90, Rat liver (RL) prep 4, and Amide-80 research, 2001 September 10 - 2005 August 5 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 92-96, and Amide-80 research, 2003 January 6 - 2008 March 19 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 97-102, 2008 October 21 - 2009 March 10 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Ortmeyer monkey urine study, Brazilian study urine samples, and INS-2 chelate preps, 1998 May 12 - 2010 June 28 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Laboratory notebook of Tie-hua Sun: NADP/NADPH samples, 2000 February 8 - 2000 March 14 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Glycerol studies, Ethanolamine analysis, and XA/XO assay, 2001 March 21 - 2005 June 29 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Rafts C/M epimerase study, and Caveoli PMT/insulin/antibody/G alpha-q (Gq) research, 2001 April 11 - 2002 January 15 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Caveoli insulin dose response results, and Gq Membrane preps, 2002 January 21 - 2002 May 21 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Liver portal vein study, Manasses Fonteles glucose reduction study, and In-Vivo INS-2 experiment, 2001 December 12 - 2006 March 3 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: PDHP assay, Padia myo-inositol/chiro-inositol tissue assay, and Gastric sleeve study, 2008 June 19 - 2010 July 14 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Bovine liver (BL) preps 73-75, and Epimerase study, 2002 November 2 - 2010 January 13 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Manasses Fonteles lab setup, Padia/Carey Anti-obesity-Hypertension study, and Epimerase study, 2008 September 4 - 2011 April 29 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: Epimerase preps, includes food chiro-inositol analysis, 2011 May 5 - 2012 October 8 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Laboratory notebook of Douglas Heimark: INS-2 chelate, B-subunit assays, and Berberine study, 2012 October 30 - 2014 May 16 (Box-folder 3:6)